Guide to the Dick Brown collection of slave records, 1789-1866 and undated, bulk 1815-1866
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Dick Brown collection of slave records 1789-1866 and undated, bulk 1815-1866
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Brown, Dick (collector)
0.2 Linear Feet 86 Items
Chiefly nineteenth-century slave records for Alabama, many for Wilcox County, and to a lesser extent for North Carolina and Virginia. Included are legal documents and other items, such as bills, receipts, wills, bonds, guardianship papers, appraisals of estates, and documents relating to the settlement of estates and to court cases. These documents contain lists of property and slaves, often with prices attached. Names and ages are usually included. Some of the receipts record items purchased for slaves and payments made for them. A group of 24 individual inventories of land and slaves in 1815 is from Virginia, and lists gender, status (e.g. child or adult), and price, but no names. Items are arranged in rough chronological order. Collected by Dick Brown.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Dick Brown collection of slave records was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1988.
Collection Overview
Chiefly nineteenth-century slave records for Alabama, many for Wilcox County, and to a lesser extent for North Carolina and Virginia. Included are legal documents and other items, such as bills, receipts, wills, bonds, guardianship papers, appraisals of estates, and documents relating to the settlement of estates and to court cases. These documents contain lists of property and slaves, often with prices attached. Names and ages are usually included. Some of the receipts record items purchased for slaves and payments made for them. A group of 24 individual inventories of land and slaves in 1815 is from Virginia, and lists gender, status (e.g. child or adult), and price, but no names. Items are arranged in rough chronological order. Collected by Dick Brown.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Child slaves -- Southern States
Executors and administrators -- Southern States
Distribution of decedents' estates -- Southern States
Inventories of decedents' estates -- Southern States
Land use -- Virginia
Probate law and practice -- Southern States
Slave bills of sale
Slave records
Slavery -- Alabama
Slavery -- North Carolina
Slavery -- Virginia
Slaves -- Alabama
Slaves -- North Carolina
Slaves -- Virginia
Alabama -- History -- 1819-1950
North Carolina -- History -- 1775-1865
Virginia -- History -- 1775-1865
Wilcox County (Ala.)--History
Contents of Collection
- Dick Brown collection of slave records, 1789-1866 and undated, bulk 1815-1866, (1 box)
  - Inventories of land and slaves in Virginia, all dated 1815 Apr. 1
    Each of the 24 inventories contains a description of land and dwellings, and a listing of unnamed slaves, listed by sex and age category. Slaves under 12 were registered as children. Slaves over 50 were registered as elderly. Arranged in original order as received.
    - John Cox, Grayson Co., $800 in land, $990 in slaves: 1 adult male, 1 adult female, 1 male child, 1 female child (Box 1)
    - Randolph Noe, Lee Co., $840 in land, $650 in slaves: 1 adult male, 1 adult female (Box 1)
    - Abraham Falkenson, Scott Co., $1172 in land, $900 in slaves: 1 adult male, 1 adult female, 1 elderly female, 1 female child (Box 1)
    - John McKeon, Lee Co., $700 in land, $250 in slaves: 1 male child (Box 1)
    - John Herring, Wythe Co., $1000 in land, $350 in slaves: 1 male child, 1 female child (Box 1)
    - John Douglas, Wythe Co., $3000 in land, $450 in slaves: 1 adult male (Box 1)
    - Robert Gallehorn, Washington Co., $900 in land, $300 in slaves: 1 female child (Box 1)
    - William Stone, Grayson Co., $640 in land, $200 in slaves: 1 male child (Box 1)
    - Thomas Smythe, Lee Co., $455 in slaves: 1 adult female, 1 female child (Box 1)
    - Capt. James Davis, Wythe Co., $1500 in land, $3000 in slaves: 4 adult males, 2 adult female, 2 male children, 2 female children (Box 1)
    - William Ellison, Washington Co., $2400 in land, $800 in slaves: 2 adult males (Box 1)
    - David Glenn, Washington Co., $1955 in land, $350 in slaves: 1 adult female (Box 1)
    - John Daak, Wythe Co., $4000 in land, $350 in slaves: 1 adult female (Box 1)
    - William Dunn, Sr., Washington Co., $1600 in land, slaves: 1 adult male $350, 2 adult females $600, 3 male children $360, 1 female child $100 (Box 1)
    - Charles Scott, Washington Co., $1500 in land, slaves: 1 adult male $300, 2 adult females $600, 3 male children $450, 3 female children $450 (Box 1)
    - David Cox, Grayson Co., $180 in land, $800 in slaves: 1 adult female, 1 male child, 2 female children (Box 1)
    - Thomas Edmiston, Washington Co., $3840 in land, slaves: 1 adult male $950, 1 adult female $350, 1 male child $100 (Box 1)
    - George W. Davis, Wythe Co., $200 in land, $2400 in slaves: 2 adult males, 2 adult females, 3 male children, 2 female children (Box 1)
    - John Huddle, Wythe Co., $1500 in land, $650 in slaves: 1 adult male, 1 adult female (Box 1)
    - Michael Brown, Wythe Co., $3000 in land, $300 in slaves: 1 adult female (Box 1)
    - James Hayes, Wythe Co., $400 in land, $500 in slaves: 1 adult female (Box 1)
    - Richard Roberts, Sr., Washington Co., $1500 in land, $900 in slaves: 2 adult males (Box 1)
    - James Breeding, Wythe Co., $1200 in land, $700 in slaves: 1 adult male, 1 male child, 1 elderly female (Box 1)
    - Estate of G. MacFarlane, Lee Co., slaves: 1 adult male $450, 1 elderly female $50 (Box 1)
  - Other Slave Records
    - 1844 May 6, Samuel Netes and Jonathan Mason: Appraisal of Jacob, a grown boy, and Ruben, a blacksmith, for $1800 (Box 1)
    - 1789 Apr. 4, Bond for 200 pounds from T. Payne to James Murdock, John Michie and G. Dabney secured by negro man Basil (Box 1)
    - 1824 Nov. 9, New Hanover Co., North Carolina, Death certificate and inventory of Archibald Taylor (Box 1)
    - 1825 Nov. 25, Lawrence Co., Alabama, Bond between Francisco Shirley and Josiah Watson secured by negro boy named Ranoul and negro girl named Betsy (Box 1)
    - 1829 Sept. 9, Letter from Gov. Forsyth re: convicted slave (Box 1)
    - 1828 Feb. 29, Alabama, Legal settlement between Abram D. Graffensico promising to pay $54 to Dudley Dunn (Box 1)
    - 1830 Aug. 9, Wilcox Co., Alabama, Will of Charles Capel, mentions negroes Allen, his wife Angey, and their children Ceasar, Altamore, and Anny; a negro boy named Albert; negroes Suky, Lanon, and Amy; provides that negroes not be hired out yearly (Box 1)
    - 1835 Oct. 17, Wilcox Co., Alabama, Report on division of Robert M. Hails estate, mentions $1400 for slaves Mary and her children George, John, and Nelson; $600 for Ann, a girl slave of fourteen and a half years (Box 1)
    - 1831 May 19, Lawrence Co., Alabama, bond for $3250 from John Moore to John M. Jackson and John MacMahon secured by 30-year-old negro man named Jim (Box 1)
    - 1833 Mar., Lawrence Co., Alabama, Complaint by John B. Watson against Charles Ewing for breach of contract re: $100 for hire of negro Clinton (Box 1)
    - 1836 Dec. 28, Promissory note from John Keys for $171 for hire of negro Charles and to furnish a slave boy (Box 1)
    - 1834 Dec. 31, Lawrence Co., Alabama, Complaint by L. Hedge against Dudley Hammond for breach of contract re: $96 for hire of negro girl Jane (Box 1)
    - 1838 May 1, Wilcox Co., Alabama, Receipt between Samuel Moore and Paul Lee for 13 pairs of negro shoes with 3 years interest for $15.23 (Box 1)
    - 1838 Dec. 28, Contract from D. Whitehead for $141 to hire negro man Daniel from estate of Asa Hodges (Box 1)
    - 1839 Jan. 22, Plantation expenses, estate of Shamburger to L. Goobold (Box 1)
    - 1839 Sept., Bond for $2429.32 from William Prewitt to John Ellis, Robert M. White, John Gregg, and James Cook secured by negro man Bob, negro boy Edmond, and negro boy Robbin (8-9 years old) (Box 1)
    - 1840 Mar. 18, Lawrence Co., Alabama, Order to expose to sale negroes James, Cooper, Bird, Sinthicum for Robert Henderson's debt to Davis Guad (Box 1)
    - 1840 Aug. 17, Bond for $153.21 and 1/2 from Davis Hunter to Andrew, George, and Martin Walter secured by 1 negro woman named Ealy (Box 1)
    - 1840 Sept. 17, Lawrence Co., Alabama, Petition of Joel Hickey for wife Susan B. Hickey (nee Jenkins) and Nancy Patterson (nee Jenkins) as heirs of Austin Jenkins for 2 negro girls Euphrasia (10) and Delia (9-10) (Box 1)
    - 1841 Mar. 8, Lawrence Co., Alabama, Bond for $1030.12 and 1/2 from F. Andres to Vinckles and Thomas Jones secured by negro John (40), his wife Isabella (40), negro woman Mary (18), and 3 children: Heawitt (7), Betty (4), and baby with yellow complexion (1), (2 versions) (Box 1)
    - 1840 Dec. 31, Monroe Co., Bill of sale for $1900 from Willis Jordan to James L. Bank for negro slaves Wade (27), his sister Mariah (31), and her daughter Ginney (10) (Box 1)
    - 1841 Jan. 26, Lawrence Co., Alabama, Bond for $324 from James A. Srice to Peter Phelps and James Wallace (Box 1)
    - 1842 Jan., Wilcox Co., Alabama, Orphan Court decision to divide negroes and horses of estate of James McMillian, negro Sam and negro girl Only (Box 1)
    - 1842 Sept. 30, Lawrence Co. Alabama, Bond for $21,250.02 from Bank of the State of Alabama to Harmon Waldorf, George Johnson, and R.P. Hughes, pending suit in circuit court regarding negroes Isaac (30), his wife Ginny (38), and their children Serena (14) and America (4), (2 versions) (Box 1)
    - 1843 Jan. 3, Wilcox Co., Alabama, List of negros belonging to minor heirs of John Satterwhite: negro man William and negro girl Mathilde ($90); negro man Buck, negro woman Lucinda, and child ($95); negro man Carrol and two children Caty and Burwell ($104.12 and 1/2) (Box 1)
    - 1844 Apr. 25, Wilcox Co., Alabama, Account of property from estate of Stephen T. Jones, including sales and hiring out of negroes Betsy ($340), Nelly, Isaac ($143), Washington ($39), Caroline ($40.50), and Salena ($11) (Box 1)
    - 1845 Oct. 23, Wilcox Co., Alabama, Estate of David McMillan, including negro man Isham ($460) (Box 1)
    - 1845 Dec. 3, Wilcox Co., Alabama, Estate of William Shanbury with a list of 25 negroes that includes name, age, and price (Box 1)
    - 1845 Dec. 30, Wilcox Co., Alabama, Complaint from Halifax Co., North Carolina (Box 1)
    - c. 1845, William M. Purifoy, guardian, account with Penelope Moor regarding hiring of Moses and Ginny for $120.25 (Box 1)
    - 1846 May 30, Wilcox Co., Alabama, Account of I. Campbell with Dr. Alison (Box 1)
    - 1846 Nov. 16, Wilcox Co., Alabama, Property appraisal of estate of Miles Malone, including negroes Alexander ($650), Dinal and 3 male children ($900), Nelson ($650), Aggy ($550), and Fanny ($525) (Box 1)
    - 1846 Sept., Lawrence Co., Alabama, William Dearing versus Hardy Winsham for mortgage default, conveyance of negro slaves (Box 1)
    - Receipt from John P. Butler to G. Logongue for maintenance of blind negro woman Bess (Box 1)
    - Marengo Co., Alabama, Mary Hill, et al. versus M. W. Creagh and Alex M. Creagh, Deposition of David Coleman regarding appraisal of sickly negroes Delila (40), Sally (40), Dick (9), Nelson (7), Clara (4). States "I would not feed and clothe the negroes for their labor." (Box 1)
    - Bill of sale from estates of Graves B. Higginbotham to Geo M. Homnes for negro girl Sarah ($576) (Box 1)
    - 1850 July 17, J.R. Grimpton, et al. versus Sarah Jane Crum and K. Dulany, answer of Dulany regarding sale of negroes (Box 1)
    - Rowan Co., North Carolina, Bond for $4000 from Alexander Donaldson, John Locke and Joseph Donaldson to Gov. Huchins Burton and successors, appointing guardian for Alexander, Frances, and Mary, children of John Penny (Box 1)
    - 1853 July 15, Wilcox Co., Alabama, Edmund Marsh versus D. Marsh et al., Deposition of Henry Pegues (Box 1)
    - 1853 July 15, Wilcox Co., Alabama, Edmund Marsh versus D. Marsh et al., Interrogatories for George F. Watson (Box 1)
    - 1854 Jan. 24, Wilcox Co., Alabama, Appraisal of estate of John Blackman, including negroes Brister ($100), Ginny and child ($900), Dareas ($400), Wash ($700), Isaac ($550), Frank ($400), and Jacob ($250) (Box 1)
    - 1854, Estate of E.B. Seltzer, sale of negro shoes (Box 1)
    - 1854 May 15, Appraisal of estate of D.L. McDonald with a list of 25 negroes that includes names, ages, and prices (Box 1)
    - 1854 Sept. 2, Wilcox Co., Alabama, Dissent of Sarah Newberry to will of Peter B. Newberry (Box 1)
    - 1854 Sept. 27, Alabama, Complaint of Joseph Harris et al. versus James Gully (Box 1)
    - 1853 Dec. 22, Wilcox Co., Alabama, Edmund Marsh versus D. Marsh et al., Deposition of Jesse P. Daniel (Box 1)
    - 1855 Sept. 10, Lawrence Co., Alabama, Order to seize slaves of William D. Suckey, Marja (15) "of dark complexion", Eliza (14) "of copper complexion" (Box 1)
    - 1855 Dec. 11, Receipt for medical care of negroes (Box 1)
    - 1857 Aug. 1, Wilcox Co., Alabama, 1828 voucher for $150 for a negro girl (age 10) received by Cynthia Cooke from E. Culpepper (Box 1)
    - 1857 Dec. 11, Wilcox Co., Alabama, B.W. Matthews versus James Robinson, Interrogatories for and response of E.H. Mobley regarding 21-year-old negro, George (Box 1)
    - 1858 Mar. 16. Receipt from H.H. Lee, Inc. to estate of Eli Mendenhall for whiskey for sick negroes (Box 1)
    - 1858 May 1, Wilcox Co., Alabama, Transfer of negro infant child (4 months) from Franklin Dirmas to J.N. Threadgill for $4.20 (Box 1)
    - 1860 May 1, Estate of W.W. McConnico regarding negroes Clarissa and her children (Box 1)
    - 1859 July 25, Wilcox Co., Alabama, Appraisal of estate of C.J. McRae, including 21-year-old John ($1500), 19-year-old Hanford (1500), 19-year-old Elick ($700), 49-year-old woman and 3-year-old child ($1166.66) (Box 1)
    - 1861 Jan. 1, Dr. J.W. Wiley bill to minor heirs of M. Philin for medical attention to negroes Jenny, Plaston, and Jenny's baby, Alfred (Box 1)
    - 1864 Jan. 18, Receipt for $60 from estate of Mary P. Kimbrough to J.W. Threadgill for 5 pairs of negro shoes (Box 1)
    - 1866 Mar. 26, Wilcox Co., Alabama, Estate of W.W. Robinson, interrogatories for creditors (Box 1)
    - 1866 Feb. 12, Wilcox Co., Alabama, Estate of W.W. Robinson, objections of creditor C.J. Dockery (Box 1)
    - James Davis for guardianship of Paris, Elisha, Elizabeth Maden, orphans of William Maden (Box 1)
    - Wilcox Co., Estate of Luke Herring regarding infant negroes "of little as no value" (Box 1)